Brenda Putnam Papers
Brenda Putnam Papers
1915-1965
Putnam, Brenda, 1890-1975.
2 linear ft.
Papers of the American sculptor and medalist. Died 1975.
The Brenda Putnam Papers consists of correspondence (1930-1959); drawings; photographs of Brenda Putnam and her work; printed material, including articles, clippings, exhibition catalogs, and reviews; reminiscences, and a sketchbook. Correspondence, predominantly incoming, includes that of the American Academy of Arts and Letters, Robert A. Baillie, Paul Philippe Cret, William Adams Delano, Eli Lilly and Company, John Flanagan, the Folger Shakespeare Library, Ossip Gabrilowitsch, Lawrence Gilman, Grand Central Art Galleries, Walker Hancock, Anna Hyatt Huntington, Archer Milton Huntington, Gertrude K. Lathrop, the Library of Congress, the Liturgical Arts Society, Edward McCartan, Harold McCracken, the Medallic Art Company, the National Academy of Design, the National Sculpture Society, Ruth Nickerson, R.H. Norton, Joan Smit, Alexander B. Trowbridge, the U.S. Mint, the Work Projects Administration, Sidney Waugh, and Louis B. Wright.
149458
Biographical History
Brenda Putnam was an American sculptor and author (1890-1975). The daughter of Herbert Putnam, a former Librarian of Congress, Brenda Putnam underscored the significance of her collection by providing not only brief annotations for various items, but often detailed reminiscences of her personal and professional life, thus establishing a context in which to view both her Papers as well as her artistic career.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Arranged chronologically from 1930 through 1959, the Correspondence includes incoming letters with holograph and typescript carbon copies of some of Brenda Putnam's outgoing responses. While illuminating her relationships with fellow artists (Robert A. Baillie, John Flanagan, James Earle Fraser, Gaetano Cecere, Walker Hancock, Anna Hyatt Huntington, Gertrude K. Lathrop, Lee Lawrie, Carl Miles, Ruth Nickerson, Henry J. Peck, Marion Sanford, Joan Smit, Carl Walters, Sidney Waugh), the Correspondence also reveals Brenda Putnam's associations with galleries and museums (Birmingham Museum of Art, Grand Central Art Galleries, New York University's Hall of Fame, Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts); patrons and sponsors of sculpture competitions (the Architect of the Capitol, the Folger Shakespeare Library, Archer M. Huntington, Eli Lilly and Company, the Liturgical Arts Society, Inc., the Medallic Art Company, R. H. Norton, the United States Director of the Mint); and professional organizations (American Academy of Arts and Letters, the National Academy of Design, the National Sculpture Society); as well as some of the subjects of her work (Harold Bauer, William Adams Delano, Ossip Gabrilowitsch). A selected index to the Correspondence follows the box list.
Artwork encompasses original drawings, reproductions of Brenda Putnam's sculpture, and sketches. In designating her work, the terminology provided by the artist has been used in the arrangement of the collection. Drawings (1918-1950) include a series of mechanical draughting exercises for a class Putnam attended prior to a taking a job with Sperry Gyroscope Company, as well as four bone-shadow drawings executed from 1947 to 1948. Arranged by title, Sculpture includes photographs and printed reproductions of Brenda Putnam's two-and three-dimensional work. Putnam's subjects range from musicians (Harold Bauer, Pablo Casals, Wanda Landowska) to law-givers (Solon, Maimonides), admirals (Ernest J. King) to feminists (Susan B. Anthony, Amelia Earhart). Much of this material is also accompanied by letters, printed material, and/or Brenda Putnam's reminiscences concerning the circumstances surrounding the execution of a particular work. Architectural pencil Sketches document Putnam's sojourn in Europe during the 1920s.
Writings include reminiscences, speeches, and miscellaneous articles, reviews, and the text for a Samuel F. B. Morse exhibition catalog. Written in 1964 and 1965, Putnam's reminiscences provide insight into her early fascination with music and musicians ("TheBeethoven Association," "A Portrait Bust of Ossip Gabrilowitsch," "Sculptor at the Piano"), while highlighting her opinions concerning her work ("Bone Shadow Drawings," "A Competition," "The Lighting of Sculpture"), often with a touch of self-deprecating humor ("The Gorilla," "Dayton, Ohio").
Memorabilia features artwork by Edgar Davies, Paul Manship, and Wheeler Williams, awards, personal photographs, printed material, and the transcript of a 1932 radio broadcast delivered shortly after the installation of Brenda Putnam's "Puck" at the Folger Shakespeare Library. Printed material includes articles and newspaper clippings (1919-1957) about Brenda Putnam, an assortment of her exhibition catalogs and invitations (1931-1947), and publicity for and reviews of her books, A Sculptor's Way and Animal X-Rays.
Arrangement of the Collection
The Brenda Putnam Papers begins with Correspondence (box 1) and is ordered by date. Artwork (boxes 1-2) follows and is grouped into the categories of drawings, sculpture and sketches. Writings (box 2) consists of reminiscences, speeches, and miscellaneous articles and reviews, all organized by date. Memorabilia starts in box 3 and is arranged alphabetically by category. A final oversized package contains some additional artwork and memorabilia (a scrapbook).
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Sculptors; Baillie, Robert A. (Robert Alexander), 1880-1961.; Cret, Paul Philippe, 1876-1945.; Delano, William Adams, 1874-1960.; Flanagan, John F., 1865-1952.; Gabrilowitsch, Ossip, 1878-1936.; Gilman, Lawrence, 1878-1939.; Hancock, Walker Kirtland, 1901-1998.; Huntington, Archer M. (Archer Milton), 1870-1955.; Huntington, Anna Hyatt, 1876-1973.; Lathrop, Gertrude Katherine, 1896-; McCartan, Edward, 1878-1947.; McCracken, Harold, 1894-1983.; Nickerson, Ruth.; Norton, R. H.; Putnam, Brenda, 1890-1975.; Smit, Joan.; Trowbridge, Alexander Buell, 1868-1950.; Waugh, Sidney, 1904-1963.; Wright, Louis B. (Louis Booker), 1899-1984.; American Academy of Arts and Letters.; Eli Lilly and Company.; Folger Shakespeare Library.; Grand Central Art Galleries.; Liturgical Arts Society.; Medallic Art Company.; National Academy of Design (U.S.); National Sculpture Society (U.S.); New York University. -- Hall of Fame.; United States. -- Work Projects Administration.; United States Mint.; Art, American.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Medalists -- United States.; Sculptors -- United States.; Sculpture, American.; Sculpture, American -- 20th century.; Women artists -- United States.; Women sculptors -- United States.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Drawings (visual works); Exhibition catalogs.; Photographs.; Reviews (documents); Sketchbooks.; Artists.; Medalists.; Sculptors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Brenda Putnam, 1964, 1968.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - General, 1930-1959; undated; 12 folders (Box 1)
- Artwork
  - Drawings
    - General, 1918; 1920; 2 items (Box 1)
    - Mechanical drawing exercises, 1942; preparation for job at Sperry Gyroscope (Oversize 1)
    - "Bone-shadow drawings", 1947-1948; 4 items (Box 1)
    - General, 1951; 1 item (Box 1)
    - "The Man from Skid Row", 1920; 1 item (Os 1)
  - Sculpture
    - "Anatomical Figure for Students", 1937 (Box 1)
    - Anthony, Susan B. (New York University Hall of Fame) (Box 1)
    - Bauer, Harold, 1949 (Box 1)
    - "Blind Beggar of Florence" (Box 1)
    - Bowker, Richard R. (Box 1)
    - Brookgreen Gardens: Sculpture by Brenda Putnam, 1937 (Box 1)
    - Casals, Pablo, 1925 (Box 1)
    - "Charmides", 1917 (Box 1)
    - "The Child in the Vineyard", 1928 (Box 1)
    - "Christ, the Light of the World", 1942 (Box 1)
    - Cleveland Centennial Great Lakes Exposition Commemorative Half-Dollar, 1936 (Box 1)
    - "Communion", mother of Robert A. Baillie (Box 1)
    - Delano, William Adams, 1950 (Box 1)
    - "Diver" (Box 1)
    - Earhart, Amelia
      - Head (Syracuse University), 1933 (Box 1)
      - Medal, 1941 (Box 1)
    - Gabrilowitsch, Ossip (Detroit Institute of Arts), 1933 (Box 1)
    - Genthe, Arnold, 1933 (Box 1)
    - Gorilla, 1944-1945 (Box 2)
    - Great Law-Givers, 1949-1950; U.S. House of Representatives plaques (Box 2)
    - Italian boy, 1927-1928; mask (Box 2)
    - "Joseph and Mary at Bethlehem", 1929 (Box 2)
    - King, Ernest Joseph, 1945-1946; medal (Box 2)
    - Kirke-Porter (Henry) memorial, 1931-1932 (Box 2)
    - Landowska, Wanda, 1928 (Box 2)
    - Lilly, Eli, 1948 (Box 2)
    - Manda (W. Albert) memorial (South Orange, NJ), 1935 (Box 2)
    - Mapother, John Rubel (Box 2)
    - "Memorial to Anne Simon" (Rock Creek Cemetery, Washington, DC), 1915 (Box 2)
    - "Memorial to the Women of Virginia (Rock Creek Cemetery, Washington, DC), 1942 (Box 2)
    - "Midsummer", 1930 (Box 2)
    - "Nature Study in Bronze", 1929 (Box 2)
    - Noble, M. C. S., 1935 (Box 2)
    - O'Hara, Desmond, 1925; nephew of Brenda Putnam (Box 2)
    - O'Hara, Jane, niece of Brenda Putnam (Box 2)
    - Post office lunette (Caldwell, NJ), 1936 (Box 2)
    - Post office mural (St. Cloud, MN), 1936 (Box 2)
    - "Puck" (Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, DC), 1931 (Box 2)
    - Putnam, Herbert (Library of Congress, Washington, DC), 1922; Father of Brenda Putnam (Box 2)
    - Sea-horse sundial, 1925 (Box 2)
    - "The Spear Dance", 1926 (Box 2)
    - "Two Kids" sundial (Brookgreen Gardens, SC), 1926 (Box 2)
    - "White Mouse with a Flea" (Box 2)
    - Woolsey, Dwight Theodore, 1931 (Box 2)
  - Sketches
    - England, F rance, 1922; 17 items (Box 2)
    - Florence, Italy, 1927; 14 items (Box 2)
    - France, Italy, 1927; 2 items (Oversize 1)
    - Sketchbook I, 1927-1929 (Box 2)
    - Sketchbook II, 1927-1929 (Box 2)
- Writings
  - Reminiscences, 1923-1926; undated (Box 2)
  - Speeches, 1964-1965; undated (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous articles, reviews, etc, 1928-1951; 2 folders (Box 2)
- Memorabilia
  - Artwork by others
    - Davies, Edgar, 7 pencil drawings (Box 3)
    - Manship, Paul, 1 pencil drawing (Box 3)
    - Williams, Wheeler, 1 pencil drawing (Box 3)
    - Unidentified, 1 page pencil drawings (Box 3)
  - Awards, 1935-1963; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Re: Beethoven Association (Box 3)
  - Financial, legal (Box 3)
  - Photographs, personal (Box 3)
  - Printed material
    - Announcement, booklet, programs, 3 programs, 1 each of others (Box 3)
    - Clippings, 1919-1957; undated; 6 folders (Box 3)
    - Exhibition catalogs, invitations, 1931-1947; undated (Box 3)
    - Publicity, reviews, miscellany
      - Animal X-rays (Box 3)
      - The Sculptor's Way (Box 3)
      - The Sculptor's Way, photograph of front cover (Oversize 1)
    - Reprints, 1949-1952; George A. Dondero speeches on communism and art from Congressional Record. (Box 3)
    - Scrapbook, 1926-1936; undated; newspaper clippings; Photocopies only. For preservation purposes, damaged originals were discarded. (Oversize 1)
  - Transcript, 1932; from radio broadcast about Brenda Putnam by Alice Hutchins Drake (Box 3)
  - Miscellany (Box 3)
Selected index to correspondence
American Academy of Arts and Letters 1939 Jul 21 1945 Feb 1
American Historical Association 1954 Oct 22 1954 Nov 1 (outgoing)
Architect of the Capitol (Washington, D.C.) see Artwork: Sculpture: Great Law-Givers: House of Representatives
Baillie, Robert A. 1945 Nov 1947 Jul 25 see also Artwork: Sculpture: "Midsummer"
Bauer, Harold 1940 Aug 8 see also Artwork: Sculpture: Bauer, Harold
Beaux-Arts Institute of Design 1940 Dec 30 1941 Jan 28
Birmingham Museum of Art 1952 Jul 22 1952 Jul 31 (outgoing) 1952 Aug 5
Burrill, Edgar 1939 Aug 8
Cecere, Gaetano 1949 Oct 1 (outgoing) 1949 Oct 3 see also Artwork: Sculpture: Great Law-Givers: House of Representatives
Cret, Paul Philippe 1932 Mar 31 see also Artwork: Sculpture: "Puck"
Delano, William Adams 1950 Mar 24 1950 Nov 10 see also Artwork: Sculpture: Delano, William Adams
Flanagan, John 1941 Jun 16 1941 Jun 20 1941 Jun 23
Folger Shakespeare Library 1946 Aug 1 1950 Jun 28 1950 Jul 2 (outgoing) 1950 Jul 5 1954 Apr 18 (outgoing Shirley Putnam O'Hara, sister of B. Putnam) 1954 Apr 21 see also Artwork: Sculpture: "Puck"
Franklin, Gilbert A. 1949 Oct 31 (outgoing) 1949 Nov 1
Fraser, James Earle 1947 Mar 12
Freigang, Paul 1940 Jul 21
Gabrilowitsch, Ossip 1932 Jan 7 1932 Mar 2 1932 Mar 8 (outgoing) 1932 Oct 19 1933 Mar 10 1933 Jun 12 1934 Mar 19 1934 Oct 17 1934 Oct 17 (secretary) 1934 Oct 19 (outgoing) undated (from Helen Brand to Ossip Gabrilowitsch) see also Artwork: Sculpture: Gabrilowitsch, Ossip
Gilman, Lawrence 1933 Feb 15 (to Mrs. [Shirley] O'Hara, sister of Brenda Putnam) 1933 Feb 18 (to Mrs. O'Hara) 1933 Feb 25
Grand Central Art Galleries 1939 Jun 6 1952 Jul 17 1958 Jul 1 1958 Jul 6 (outgoing)
Grolier Society Inc. 1950 Dec 27 1951 Mar 7 1952 Oct 7
Hall of Fame: New York University see New York University. Hall of Fame
Hancock, Walker 1948 Aug 24 1949 Nov 15 see also Artwork: Sculpture: "Christ, the Light of the World"
Huntington, Anna Hyatt 1947 Sep 29 (copy of Herbert Putnam letter to A. H. Huntington) 1947 Nov 14 1948 Apr 4 (outgoing) 1948 Apr 6 1948 May 29 1949 Oct 11 (outgoing) 1950 Mar 24
Huntington, Archer Milton 1939 Jun 22 1947 May 15 1947 Sep 29 (copy of Herbert Putnam memorandum to A. M. Huntington) 1948 Apr 4 (outgoing)
Jennewein, Carl Paul 1949 Dec 27
Johnson, Robert Underwood 1934 Mar 14
Lathrop, Gertrude K. 1933 Jun 14 1939 Jul 10 1948 Apr 21 (outgoing) 1948 [Apr] (with previous letter)
Lawrie, Lee 1949 Oct 7 1949 Nov 14 1950 Mar 10 (outgoing) 1950 Mar 14 1952 Apr 2 see also Artwork: Sculpture: Great Law-Givers: House of Representatives
Library of Congress 1931 Dec 23 1932 Mar 11 1932 Apr 5 1951 Oct 12 (outgoing) 1951 Oct 24 see also Artwork: Sculpture: "Puck"
Eli Lilly and Company 1948 May 24 1948 Jun 29 1948 Jun 30 1948 Jul 22 1948 Aug 6 (outgoing) 1948 Aug 13 1948 Aug 25 1948 Sep 4 (outgoing) 1948 Sep 13 1948 Sep 24 (outgoing) 1948 Oct 4 see also Artwork: Sculpture: Lilly, Eli
Liturgical Arts Society, Inc. 1941 Dec 17 1942 Feb 21 1942 Mar 4 (outgoing) 1942 Mar 17 1942 Jul 23 see also Artwork: Sculpture: "Christ, the Light of the World"
Lynn, David (Architect of the Capitol, Washington, D.C.) see Artwork: Sculpture: Great Law-Givers: House of Representatives
Lyons, Bertha L. see New York University: Hall of Fame
McCartan, Edward 1941 Aug 25 1941 Aug 27 (outgoing)
McCracken, Harold 1949 Dec 19 (attached to undated outgoing)
Medallic Art Company 1941 Apr 16 1942 Apr 9 1950 Jan 4
Miles, Carl 1947 Feb 24
National Academy of Design 1935 Mar 9 1941 Aug 25 1941 Aug 27 (outgoing)
National Arts Club 1947 Nov 14
National Sculpture Society 1938 May 24 (copy of letter to Special Deputy Comptroller) 1951 Sep 13 1952 Jan 21 1953 Feb 13
New York University. Hall of Fame 1934 Mar 14 1951 Dec 10 (outgoing) 1951 Dec 13 1952 Jan 31 (outgoing) 1952 Jan 28 1952 Feb 4 1952 Apr 21 1952 Apr 28 1952 May 1 1952 May 22 see also Artwork: Sculpture: Anthony, Susan B.
Nichols, Hobart 1947 Nov 1 (outgoing) 1947 Nov 10
Nickerson, Ruth undated undated (fragment)
Norton, R. H. 1945 Sep 22 (outgoing) 1945 Oct 28 (outgoing) 1945 Nov 2 1946 Jul 19 1946 Sep 17 1946 Sep 23 (outgoing) 1946 Nov 12 see also Artwork: Sculpture: "Midsummer"
Peck, Henry J. 1939 Oct 1
Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts 1940 Feb 21 1940 Feb 26 (outgoing) 1940 Feb 28
Sanford, Marion 1948 Jan 15 (outgoing)
The Saturday Review 1952 Mar 29 (outgoing)
Smit, Joan 1950 Apr 15 1950 Nov 25
Society of Medalists 1942 Nov 10
Stewart, J. George 1958 May 8 1958 Jun (outgoing) 1958 Jun 17 see also Artwork: Sculpture: Great Law-Givers: House of Representatives
Sullivan, Francis P. see Artwork: Sculpture: Great Law-Givers: House of Representatives
Louis Comfort Tiffany Foundation 1947 Nov 1 (outgoing) 1947 Nov 10
Trees, Clyde C. see Medallic Art Company
Trowbridge, Alexander B. 1930 May 7 [1931] Oct 22 1932 Apr 2 (to Herbert Putnam) 1932 Apr 14 see also Artwork: Sculpture: "Puck"
United States. Director of the Mint 1946 Aug 1 1946 Dec 3 1946 Dec 16 (outgoing) 1947 Jan 23 1947 May 2 see also Artwork: Sculpture: King, Ernest Joseph (medal)
United States. Work Projects Administration 1940 Sep 26 1940 Sep 27 (outgoing)
Vanamee, Grace 1939 Jul 21
Van Kirk, Florence M. P. 1939 Oct 5
Walters, Carl 1939 Jul 2
Waugh, Sidney 1946 Dec 4
Wright, Louis B. 1950 Jun 28 1950 Jul 2 (outgoing) 1950 Jul 5 1954 Apr 18 (outgoing Shirley Putnam O'Hara, sister of B. Putnam) 1954 Apr 21 see also Artwork: Sculpture: "Puck"